Guide to the United Orthodox Synagogues records, 1935-2023 MS 712
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
United Orthodox Synagogues records
1935-2023
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
United Orthodox Synagogues of Houston (Houston, Tex.)
MS 712
9 Linear Feet 8 boxes, 1 map-drawer folder
This collection is made up of eight boxes containing books, bulletins, correspondence, event materials, financial records, flyers, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, photographs, plaques, programs, scrapbooks, videos, and yearbooks from United Orthodox Synagogues spanning from 1935 to 2023.
Biographical / Historical
The United Orthodox Synagogues of Houston was formed in 1965 when two separate synagogues, Adath Emeth and Beth Jacob, joined together. Congregation Adath Israel joined the United Orthodox Synagogues a year later.
The oldest of the founding congregations, Adath Israel, was formed in 1905 because observant Jews living in Houston's Fifth Ward lived too far away to walk to Adath Yeshurun. Members first met in the Wertheimer home until they dedicated their first synagogue building in 1910. From 1910 to 1930 Adath Israel was led by Rabbi Jacob Geller. In 1939 the congregation moved to a new building in Washington Terrace.
Adath Emeth was formed in 1908 and officially chartered in 1910. Like many synagogues in South Texas, Adath Emeth had its first services in the homes of members, rather than in a synagogue building. In its early years the congregation was led by shochet and cantor Meyer Epstein. Services moved to a house on Artesian Place near Preston Avenue, then to "the upstairs of a feed store" on Preston Avenue near the current downtown area, just North of Buffalo Bayou. After World War I the congregation built a wooden synagogue at Houston and Washington Avenue, but it burned down after only two years. That same year, 1923, the congregation built a more permanent structure in the same place, which would remain their synagogue building until 1948, when they erected a new building at Cleburne and Ennis in the Third Ward. In 1959 they sold their building to Texas Southern University, and moved to their present location on Greenwillow Drive at South Braeswood, in the Willow Meadows neighborhood in southwest Houston. The records we have between 1960 and 1965 show that Adath Emeth was an active community with a Sisterhood, N.C.S.Y, frequent parties and events, and a theatre troupe. Although the congregation officially joined with Beth Jacob and later Adath Israel in the mid-1960s, they maintained their own separate identity for years after the merger, even holding their own 50 Year Golden Jubilee Anniversary in 1968.
Beth Jacob was formed in 1937 in the home of Rabbi Max Geller to form a Modern Orthodox congregation designed "to serve the Jews residing in the South End of the city of Houston," according to the synagogue's board minutes. Twenty-three men comprised the first chartering members. That year the congregation bought land at Cleburne and Hamilton and in two years built their synagogue there. Elsewhere in the Houston Jewish History Archives is a large service flag from Beth Jacob Congregation, which includes the names of members and affiliated persons who served in the armed forces during World War II.
In 1965 because of dwindling membership and financial issues, Beth Jacob and Adath Emeth joined, followed by Adath Israel in 1966. United Orthodox Synagogues was led by Rabbi Raphael Schwartzman and Cantor Irving Dean. In the 1970s Rabbi Schwartzman left the congregation and was replaced by Rabbi Kenneth Hain, followed by Rabbi Joseph Radinsky, who served UOS from 1976 to 2003. Since 2003, Rabbi Barry Gelman has served as UOS's spiritual leader.
Scope and Contents
Books, bulletins, correspondence, event materials, financial records, flyers, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, photographs, plaques, programs, scrapbooks, videos, and yearbooks document the formation and history of the United Orthodox Synagogues from 1935 to 2023. Of particular interest are the organization's founding documents, several scrapbooks and photo albums, and videos of the congregation throughout the 1960s and 70s. The materials are largely in good condition and would be of particular interest to researchers interested in Houston Jewish institutions, Adath Emeth, Adath Israel, Beth Jacob, or individuals Rabbi Schwartzmann and Cantor Irving Dean.
This collection forms part of the South Texas Jewish Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection open for research; however, meeting minutes and some financial records from more recent years have been restricted until 2070. Permission to view these items must be obtained from the director of the Houston Jewish History Archive or the director of the Woodson Research Center.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586. Allow 24 hours retrieval time.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The United Orthodox Synagogues donated the collection in June of 2018; May 2023.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in four series as follows: Series I: Adath Emeth, Series II: Adath Israel, Series III: Beth Jacob, Series IV: United Orthodox Synagogues, Series V: Oversize, Series VI: Addenda
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life; Orthodox Jewish Congregations of America; Religion
Document Types
books; Correspondence; Minutes (Records); photographs; Albums (Books); Video recordings; yearbooks; Records (documents)
Places
Texas -- Houston
Subjects (Corporations)
United Orthodox Synagogues of Houston (Houston, Tex.); United Orthodox Synagogues of Houston (Houston, Tex.)
- Series I: Adath Emeth
  - Subseries A: Books
    - Adath Emeth Cemetery Information Book, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Adath Emeth Cemetery Information Book, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Adath Emeth Golden Jubilee Book, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries B: Bulletins
    - Adath Emeth Bulletins, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries C: Correspondence
    - Adath Emeth Letters, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries D: Event Materials
    - Adath Emeth Event Materials, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries E: Flyers
    - Adath Emeth Flyers, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries F: Minutes
    - Adath Emeth Minutes, 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Adath Emeth Minutes, 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Adath Emeth Minutes, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subseries G: Newspaper Clippings
    - Adath Emeth Newspaper Clippings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries H: Photographs
    - Adath Emeth Photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Adath Emeth "Honoring the Sisterhood Officers" Photos, 1963-01-09 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Adath Emeth Installation Dance, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Adath Emeth "Malka Ropes a Texan" Photos, 1963-03-23-1963-03-24 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Rabbi Schwartzman's 11th Anniversary, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Subseries I: Videos
    - Adath Emeth "Purim Spele- Men in Drag" VHS Video (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Subseries J: Yearbooks
    - Adath Emeth Sisterhood Yearbook, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Subseries K: Scrapbooks
    - NCSY Scrapbook, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Series II: Adath Israel
  - Subseries A: Administrative Records
    - Adath Israel Conveyance to United Orthodox Synagogues Cemetery, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series III: Beth Jacob
  - Subseries A: Minutes
    - Beth Jacob Minutes, 1937-1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Beth Jacob Board of Education Meeting Minutes, 1939-1944 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Beth Jacob Minutes, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Beth Jacob Minutes, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Beth Jacob Minutes, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series IV: United Orthodox Synagogues
  - Subseries A: Administrative Records
    - Torah Scrolls Inventory and Condition Report (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - United Orthodox Synagogues Plans and Operations (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - United Orthodox Synagogues Architectural Plans, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Houston Kashruth Assn. and Olympic Bakery (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Sisterhood Board, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Men's Club, 1993-1997 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - UOS Mission and Goals Statement (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Memorial List of Names, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Subseries B: Books
    - UOS Sisterhood "Kosher Menus with Recipes to Match", 1973 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Nesim All Around Me" The Life of David Mitzner, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Book of Remembrance, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Tribute Book to Cantor Irving Dean, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Subseries C: Bulletins
    - UOS Bulletins, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1971-1972-09-30 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1972-10-01-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1982-1984-04-30 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1984-05-01-1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1986-1987-06-30 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1987-07-01-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1989-1990-04-30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1990-05-01-1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - UOS Bulletins, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - UOS Bulletins, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - UOS Bulletins, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - UOS Bulletins, 2004-2005 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - UOS Bulletins, 2006-2008 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Bulletin Resources, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Subseries D: Correspondence
    - UOS Letters, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Sisterhood Blank Cards, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Sisterhood Invitations, 1996-2000 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Subseries E: Financial Records
    - Fundraising (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Sisterhood Financial Info, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Subseries F: Flyers
    - UOS Flyers, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Subseries G: General
    - "A Halachik Guide to Cleaning and Kashering for Pesach", 2008 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Jewish Heritage Calendar, 2007-2008 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Subseries H: Minutes
    - UOS Minutes, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1967-07-01-1970-01-31 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1970-03-01-1973-12-31 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1974-1977 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes and Financial Information, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Sisterhood Meeting Minutes, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Architectural Meeting Minutes, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2014-2016 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Subseries I: Newspaper Clippings
    - UOS Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Portion of Jewish Herald Voice, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 2005-2006 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Jewish Herald Voice Ads, 2004-2006 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Complimentary Edition of the Jewish Press, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Subseries J: Pamphlets
    - UOS Endowment Fund Pamphlet (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Southwest Region UOJ 2nd Annual Hyman Danziger Memorial Retreat, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Subseries K: Photographs
    - Consecration Photos, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Photograph Negatives, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Sisterhood Photo Album, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Sisterhood Photos, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Photographs, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Photographs, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Photographs, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Subseries L: Plaques
    - Plaques from UOS Building, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Plaques from UOS Building, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Yahrzeit and Memorial Plaque Lists, 2008 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Subseries M: Programs
    - Sculpture Dedication Program, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "An Evening of Gratitude" Rabbi Joseph and Juliette Radinsky, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Chai Anniversary Dinner Honoring Rabbi and Mrs. Radinsky, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Gala Dinner Honoring David Mitzner, 2009 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Cantor's Concert, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Cantor Irving Dean Celebrating 50 Years, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "Tree of Life", 1992 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Tribute to Members, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Johannesburg Jewish Male Choir, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Subseries N: Scrapbooks
    - UOS Sisterhood Scrapbook, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Schwartzman Scrapbook, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Subseries O: Videos
    - Sisterhood of UOS Fashion Show Video, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Subseries P: Yahrzeit Records
    - Yahrzeit Records (1 of 4), 1974 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Yahrzeit Records (2 of 4), 1974 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Yahrzeit Records (3 of 4), 1974 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Yahrzeit Records (4 of 4), 1974 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Series V: Oversize
  - Two oversize cloth blueprints of cemetery lots (Map-drawer 189, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Addenda
  - Photograph of Elie Gelman's bris, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - UOS Commissions the Writing of a New Sefer Torah flyer, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence from Senator John Cornyn regarding Hurricane Harvey damage, 2018-02-04 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Jewish Herald Voice articles, 2021-2023 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Groundbreaking Ceremony program and booklet, 2022-09-18 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - printed sermon, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Cantor Irving Dean audio cassette: Musical Memories, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - UOS Cantor's Concert featuring Herschel and Judy Fox booklet, 1991-06-09 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Shabbat bulletin, 2018-04-20-2018-04-21 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Pandemic outdoor tent service materials, 2020 (Box 8, Folder 27)